Brian H. Rutledge

Software Developer and Technologist Arlington, MA

617-955-7782 <u>brian@bhrutledge.com</u> <u>http://linkedin.com/in/bhrutledge</u> <u>http://github.com/bhrutledge</u>

I enjoy learning software systems, using them to solve problems, and explaining their concepts and usage. I'm looking for opportunities to do that with a team of people working on solutions that will improve people's lives.

I was an embedded software engineer for three years, then left the industry in 2005 to pursue people-oriented work. I was fortunate to find it at a large bike shop, where I've enjoyed the flow of a variety roles, from selling bikes to administering software, all focused on connecting our customers with cycling. In my free time, I have expanded my software development skills by building responsive websites back-to-front.

Skills

Adapting, Assimilating, Coding, Communicating, Debugging, Editing, Explaining, Learning, Programming, Researching, Teaching, Training, Troubleshooting

Software Development: Python, SQL, Git, Linux/Unix, Test-Driven Development

Web Development: Django, Flask, Selenium, PHP, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, Responsive Design, Typography

Experience

Freelance

Full Stack Web Developer

2006-Present

- Developed a <u>Flask web application</u> to transform CSV files into HTML tables with jQuery sorting and searching
- Developed Django applications and built a band website
- Developed a PHP framework for quickly building brochure websites
- Designed, developed, and deployed static brochure websites with responsive layouts
- Built a personal website with Pelican

Belmont Wheelworks Belmont, MA

IT Operations Manager

2007-Present

- Configured and managed the MindBody web application to replace a paper binder for appointment booking
- Configured and managed Google Apps for email, calendars, documents, and intranet
- Managed a major upgrade of the CounterPoint retail management software
- Wrote Python scripts to sync store inventory to website catalog
- Wrote SQL queries and Python scripts to generate custom reports of customers and inventory

- Developed a physical count procedure and data collection utility to improve inventory accuracy
- Built and managed the <u>business website</u> using the SmartEtailing CMS and developed a custom front-end with CSS and JavaScript
- Built a <u>Squarespace website</u> for the in-house frame builder
- Established and managed the relationship with an IT consulting firm to ensure timely and competent network management for all locations
- Provided IT vendors with on-site troubleshooting and new project scopes
- Provided staff training and support for all software systems

Bicycle Fitter 2009–Present

- Improved clients' riding position through bicycle adjustments and coaching
- Completed bicycle fitting certification programs from SBCU, SICI, and Retül

Buyer 2006–Present

- Ordered and stocked electronics, saddles, nutrition, and media
- Trained staff and customers on electronics

Salesperson 2006–Present

- Managed customer relationships by email, phone, and appointment
- Sold bicycles, clothing, accessories, and parts

Darwin's Ltd. Cambridge, MA

Buyer, Sandwich Maker, Barista

2005-2006

- · Ordered and stocked raw ingredients and paper goods
- Prepared and served beverages and sandwiches

Applied Innovation Inc.

Dublin, OH

Software Engineer 2002–2005

- Assumed sole development responsibility for a troubled network device, turning it into a major new source of income
- Designed, developed, and documented new features for network devices using 68k Assembly, C, C++, Java, and Python
- Designed and executed test plans for network devices
- Completed several minor software releases as sole developer
- Completed several major software releases on a small team
- Diagnosed and addressed field issues in conjunction with customer service

Software Engineering Intern

 Designed and developed a Perl web application for automated regression testing of network devices Nationwide Services Company Columbus, OH 2000 **Unix System Administrator Intern** • Assisted with server maintenance and testing third-party software • Studied Perl, the Unix environment, and system administration tools The Ohio State University Columbus, OH **System Operations Center Operator** 2000-2002 • Responded to help requests in a Unix and Windows environment • Designed and developed a graphic FAQ editor in Java 2000 **Lab Consultant** • Provided programming and Unix assistance to students in labs of 50-100 computers 1999-2000 **Grader** • Graded papers for an introductory software development course in C++ • Provided guidance for 35-40 students during and outside of class

Education

The Ohio State University

Bachelor of Science, Computer & Information Science

2002

• Graduated Cum Laude with Honors in the Liberal Arts, 3.640 GPA